<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflections upon Mr. Stephens's sermon, preach'd before the Honourable House of Commons, at St. Margaret's Church in Westminster, January the 30th, 1699/700 by a gentleman who took the said sermon in short-hand.</title>
            <author>Gentleman who took the said sermon in short-hand.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58375</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12818227</idno>
  <idno type="VID">94176</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240958597</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R721</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8547</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12818227</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94176)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 776:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflections upon Mr. Stephens's sermon, preach'd before the Honourable House of Commons, at St. Margaret's Church in Westminster, January the 30th, 1699/700 by a gentleman who took the said sermon in short-hand.</title>
                  <author>Gentleman who took the said sermon in short-hand.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the use of the Calves-head Club, in order to their conversion,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Stephens, William, d. 1718. --  Sermon preached before the Honourable House of Commons, January 30, 1699/700.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:94176:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:94176:1"/>
            <p>Reflections UPON Mr. <hi>STEPHENS</hi>'s Sermon, Preach'd before the Honourable House of COMMONS, AT St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s Church in <hi>Westminster, January</hi> the 30th. 1699/700.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Gentleman who took the said Sermon in Short-Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Use of the Calves-Head Club, in order to their Conversion.</p>
            <p>Price Six Pence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:94176:2"/>
            <p>REFLECTIONS UPON Mr. <hi>STEPHENS</hi>'s Sermon, Preach'd before the Honourable House of COMMONS, <hi>January</hi> the 30th, 1699/700.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:94176:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:94176:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:94176:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94176:4"/>
            <head>Reflections UPON Mr. <hi>STEPHENS</hi>'s Sermon, Preach'd before the Honourable House of COMMONS, AT St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s Church in <hi>Westminster, January</hi> the 30th. 1699.</head>
            <p>AMONG all the various kinds of <hi>Seditious</hi> People, that from time to time have <hi>Plagu'd</hi> our <hi>English</hi> Nation, there have been none so dreadfully Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious and Troublesome to the Peace of <hi>England,</hi> as our <hi>Government Menders,</hi> who always find something that they think ought to be Altered, Amended, or Abolished, and are so fond of their own <hi>Enthusiastick</hi> Notions, which rather proceed from <hi>Over-heated Brains,</hi> than <hi>Solid</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:94176:5"/> that they can neither be at quiet themselves, nor suffer any Societies of Men to be so, that will but hearken whilst they are communicating their own fansiful Delusions, and <hi>Whims</hi> that have no other Design than to distract the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Politick. These Practices have been formerly Arraign'd, as the Crimes of particular <hi>Laymen,</hi> that Courted <hi>Preferment</hi> by setting up themselves as profest <hi>Enemies</hi> to every Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistration; but now to find this Course pursued by a Man that has the Reputation of Learning, a Batchelor in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and Beneficed in the <hi>Church of England,</hi> is so <hi>Abominable</hi> and <hi>Amazing,</hi> that 'tis enough to startle Men of Temper and Prudence, to think the Church should harbour such a <hi>Viper</hi> in its <hi>Bosom,</hi> as is gnawing his way to a <hi>Name,</hi> by M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thods directly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pposite to his own <hi>Oaths of Fidelity, Canonical Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and the Purity of the Churches Doctrine,</hi> which unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily came to pass after this manner.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> being ambitious of getting a Name among a Party that never wish'd well to the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> or the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> knowing the <hi>Honourable and Loyal House of Commons</hi> did Annually meet at <hi>St.</hi> Margaret<hi>'s Church in</hi> West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster, on the 30th of <hi>January,</hi> to bewail a Crime so dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted by God and Man, as the Murder of a King is, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured the Favour of Preaching before that <hi>Honourable Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> on that Solemn Day of Humiliation, in which so black a Crime was committed, which had it not long since been publickly appointed by the Voice of the <hi>whole Nation,</hi> that we, and our Posterities after us, should Yearly bewail the <hi>Guilty Memory</hi> of it, it would have remain'd, an <hi>Indelible Disgrace</hi> to the present Age, and to the whole <hi>English</hi> Name; and yet the reason, as 'tis credibly reported, why h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Honour of Preaching before this <hi>August Assembly</hi> on that occasion, was, <hi>Because he thought himself able, to give that Wife and Illustrious Auditory, sufficient Reasons for the Non-observance of it any longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:94176:5"/>
            <p>A Bold, Saucy, and Daring undertaking, to Preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst a Law in force, before our <hi>Legislators;</hi> as if they knew not what was fit to be <hi>Retained</hi> or <hi>Abolished,</hi> without the Directions of a <hi>Pragmatical Preacher,</hi> that like a <hi>Blind,</hi> and Bewildred Traveller, seems to have lost his way; and whilst he affected to <hi>Dictate</hi> so Magisterially out of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Road and Duty of a Preacher,</hi> he fell into a Complication of Absurdities: Each of which was a most intolerable Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in his Politicks, and may chance raise a Storm upon him, that all the Friends he has will never be able to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cify.</p>
            <p>Of all Men living, Mr. <hi>Stephens,</hi> considering his own <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances,</hi> had the greatest reason in the World to have worn out his Days in the greatest <hi>Obscurity;</hi> and it not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuses his own Discretion, but the Common <hi>Prudence</hi> of all his Advisers; to revive the Memory of his <hi>former</hi> (and almost buried) <hi>Crimes,</hi> by setting him up in such a Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Auditory, which would carry the Discourse of them into all the Counties and Corporations of <hi>England,</hi> had he beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himself never so cautiously in the Pulpit: And what then might he reasonable expect, when he resolved to <hi>Affront the Laws,</hi> and run counter to the Sentiments of the whole Kingdom; but that his <hi>Abominable and not to be named Crimes, with which he was accused by his Scholars, when he was School-Master of</hi> Bristol, <hi>and for which he run away from that City for fear of being Prosecuted,</hi> should be revived to his Eternal Infamy, and Hatred of all Mankind. Which if his Advisers had considered, they would never have cast such an <hi>Odium</hi> upon their own <hi>Tennets</hi> and <hi>Politicks,</hi> as to have publish'd them by a Man of Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi>'s Character.</p>
            <p>However, up he comes with his <hi>Usual</hi> Confidence into St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s Pulpit, and having named his Text out of <hi>Titus</hi> the 3d, Verse the 1st, <hi>Put them in mind to be subject to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and Powers, to obey Magistrates, and to be ready to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:94176:6"/> every Good Work:</hi> Which Text in its genuine Interpretation imports nothing else, but that all <hi>Christians</hi> should Peaceably submit themselves to the Government under which they live: yet he that always had the <hi>Ill luck</hi> to spy more in a Text than all the rest of his Brethren, indeavoured to prove (tho' with very ill success) the Doctrine of <hi>Disobedience</hi> to Princes, from the same Text that Preaches up Obedience to Authority, as the <hi>Indispensible</hi> Duty of every <hi>Christian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not say he urg'd Resistance in <hi>Express Words,</hi> for there was a vein of <hi>Crafty</hi> and <hi>Ambiguous</hi> Sence and Expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that run through his whole <hi>Sermon,</hi> which might have fitted the Mouth of a <hi>Knox,</hi> or a <hi>Mariana,</hi> but ill became one that would be thought a Minister of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> and a true Son of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> He has indeed a peculiar Knack at wounding with Sly, Oblique, and Paltry Suggesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; at Stabbing and looking another way, as if he were wholly Innocent and Unconcern'd, which might pass at a Tables end over a <hi>Bottle</hi> amongst his <hi>Cronies</hi> of the Faction; but he was mightily mistaken, to think he could Top upon a whole Parliament, or so disguise his Notions, that they could not apprehend that his Raking up the pretended faults of <hi>Afflicted Majesty,</hi> was a Base and Cowardly Assault, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more than Barbarous and Inhumane; and his Leveling the Supreme Authority below its just Rights, was but a trick to usher in <hi>Confusion,</hi> or which is worse, beget a misunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing between the Royal Head and Loyal Members, as if they would incroach upon the Sovereignty, and therefore those great Men put such a Slight upon this <hi>Confident Preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricator,</hi> as would have broken any <hi>English</hi> Man's Heart, but Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi>'s, or at least have made him follow his <hi>Bristol</hi> Brother in Iniquity <hi>Emanuel Heath,</hi> into <hi>Jamaica,</hi> who both fled from <hi>Bristol</hi> almost at the same time, and upon the very same occasion.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:94176:6"/>
            <p>It cannot be imagined I should answer every <hi>Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox</hi> Notion in his <hi>Sermon;</hi> I shall therefore only reflect upon the main Design, and be indebted to him for the rest, till he Prints his Sermon.</p>
            <p>His Flurting at the Doctrine of <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> was only putting Swords into the Hands of Madmen, who know no other use of it, but either to destroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, or the Peace of the Kingdom; for no Man can have any honest Design that Preaches against it. 'Tis true, the Words were abused in the late Reign, and is at all times when employ'd to countenance an <hi>Insupportable Tyranny,</hi> and that has made the Words generally <hi>distast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> to <hi>English</hi> Men since the Revolution; which all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monarchists being sensible of, when they have a mind to inveigh against <hi>Obedience to Authority,</hi> 'tis but Tack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word <hi>Passive</hi> to <hi>Obedience,</hi> and their Work is done: For it creates an Aversion in unthinking People, who cannot distinguish between the Use and the Abuse of things; and because 'twas once applied to Ill Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, run away with that mistake <hi>ad infinitem,</hi> and think the Men that inveigh against <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> are the only Asserters of true <hi>English</hi> Liberty: Which is a grand mistake, and instead of lulling Men asleep in an Error so pernicious to the Peace of the Kingdom, ought to Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm this Stupid Humour into a sense of Danger, or the Folly will be as unaccountable, as the Mischiefs will be insupportable, if ever this <hi>Seditious Hot-headed</hi> Crew of Republicans, be once more suffered to have the Steerage of Publick Affairs; who are a Proud and Ambitious sort of People, only valuable in their Conceits, and now <hi>Herd</hi> with the <hi>Jacobites</hi> only to reduce us into a State of <hi>Anarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:94176:7"/>
            <p>Some Men through Ignorance might imbibe Notions of Disobedience, as others think it lawful upon extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Occasions, where <hi>Sic Volo sic Jubeo</hi> is a Law, and the King's Will is made the Political Standard; but for a Man of Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi>'s Learning, to Preach up the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Resistance in a time of Peace, when there is no occasion to blow the Coals, when we have a King of our own choice, whom the Nation intirely Love and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as being a <hi>Valiant</hi> and <hi>Brave Prince,</hi> undoubtedly the greatest <hi>Heroe</hi> of his Age, and has a <hi>Soul</hi> large e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to <hi>Animate</hi> more than three Kingdoms, was such an Ungenerous, Dastardly, and creeping Innuendo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him, and carried such a rude threatning of His Majesty, if he should happen to disoblige the Faction; that the Preacher ought to be treated with a Scorn, and Contempt, answerable to the Baseness of the Enterprize: Since he cannot but know, that the <hi>Doctrines of Passive Obedience and Non-Resistance</hi> in their just Latitude, and Evangelical Importance, are Truths as <hi>Sacred</hi> as any other Humane Duty in the <hi>Bible,</hi> and without the Belief and Practice of it, the World will be no better than a <hi>Savage</hi> Wilderness, and a Habitation of <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> in Humane Shape, Rending and Devouring one another.</p>
            <p>To accomplish this wicked End must needs be the great Design of our Popular Orator; for tho' he so flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently harangu'd about the tremendous Consequences of <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> he studiously conceal'd the fatal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequences of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which will be ever found to be more Durable and Mischievous. This St. <hi>Paul</hi> well knew, and therefore founded this important and Inviolable Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:94176:7"/> upon Reasons that are perpetual and unalterable, as namely, that the Supream Magistrate is the Ordinance of God; His Power is ordain'd of God; He is the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of the great Immutable God, and not of the Gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Capricious Multitude: Now these Reasons hold good equally at all times, subsist under all the Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the World, are the same now in <hi>England</hi> that they were heretofore at <hi>Rome,</hi> and consequently the Duty of Obedience must be the same, Yesterday, to Day, and for ever. And yet what pains has Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> taken to lessen, if not incourage (by slant Strokes) the Crying and Diabolical Sin of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which is so Dangerous, and infinitely encroaching, that if it be not stifled in its <hi>Seed</hi> and <hi>Principle,</hi> it will when kindled bid defiance to all Controul, and run along like an irresistible Confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration: And tho' the <hi>Preacher</hi> employ'd all his Art in Mincing and Palliating the Matter, 'twill be found a Maxime of Eternal Varity, that whosoever gives Power to any Subjects to rise up against a Good King, or Preach it up as lawful so to do, gives <hi>License</hi> to others to re-act the same <hi>doleful Tragedy</hi> which the whole Land mourns for every Thirtieth of <hi>January.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preachers next Design was to assert the <hi>Liberty of the Subject,</hi> an excellent thing when Honestly used, and Peaceably intended; but to what purpose he insisted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Topick now, when blessed be God we have a <hi>Prince</hi> that neither does, nor intends to infringe our <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges,</hi> or Deprive us of our <hi>Rights,</hi> but has given us all the Legal Securities a Parliament could ask for our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Peace and Happiness. When there are no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints that our <hi>Rights</hi> are Invaded, our <hi>Properties</hi> U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surped, or our <hi>Liberties</hi> Infringed, and the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:94176:8"/> sit under their own Vines in Peace and Tranquility, I cannot imagine, unless he intended to Introduce a <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luine Liberty,</hi> for Men to say and do what they please: A Liberty of <hi>affronting</hi> the Government, and of impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and practising upon invented <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Possibilities,</hi> till they have brought us into Vassalage to their own Party.</p>
            <p>Now to Antidote this <hi>Venome,</hi> and to shield our selves from the Danger and Delusion, so artificially Insinuated by our <hi>Bifarious Predicator,</hi> is to judge of the Designs by the Men that promotes them; for all the Arts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by our Enemies, tho' never so cunningly disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, are but the Sly Impositions of Cunning Knaves, to advance their own Party: And therefore when we see ill Men take up a fit of pretended Zeal, and Kindness for their Country, and appear better <hi>Natured</hi> than consists with their <hi>Principles</hi> and avowed <hi>Interests,</hi> 'tis time to suspect a <hi>Fraud,</hi> and weigh their <hi>Words</hi> with their <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices,</hi> before we believe them further than consists with the safety of the Government, for the <hi>Men</hi> and their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs</hi> can never be parted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liberty</hi> is the greatest Glory of a People; yet if it be not bounded by the Laws of <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> 'tis the greatest <hi>Makebate</hi> in the World, and tends directly to the Ruine of every Community, by the known Rule, <hi>That the best things corrupted become the worst.</hi> Liberty perverted into <hi>Contention</hi> for Superiority, is but <hi>Trapan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Deluding Men</hi> into <hi>Real Slavery;</hi> Catching them with <hi>Words,</hi> and Decoying them into Nets and <hi>Snares:</hi> 'Twas the Affectation of this, that made our first Parents <hi>Rebel</hi> against <hi>God,</hi> and prompted Seditious Men, to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:94176:8"/> against his <hi>Vicegerents</hi> on Earth: 'Twas a Sin of this Complexion, that occasion'd the Unparallell'd Murder of <hi>Charles the First,</hi> for which our Land mourns at this very Day, and which seems like the first Transgression, to continue a lasting Curse and Debt upon Posterity.</p>
            <p>Another Obliging Instance of his Dear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects to <hi>Monarchy,</hi> was <hi>Investing the Sovereign and Supream Power in the People,</hi> and how that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sists with his Duty as a Subject, or with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated <hi>Oaths</hi> as a <hi>Clergyman,</hi> I leave him to Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and Repent of, least he falls under an <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Censure</hi> also.</p>
            <p>Sure Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> when he was advancing the <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Power of the People,</hi> thought he was Preaching at <hi>Wootton-Under-Edge</hi> in <hi>Gloucestershire,</hi> where he us'd to Vend these Popular Notions by <hi>Wholesale,</hi> with now and then a Gird at the <hi>Establish'd Church,</hi> to make his Discourse more Palatable to the Carders and Spin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and not in <hi>St.</hi> Margaret<hi>'s Church</hi> at <hi>Westminster,</hi> whose Auditors were not accustomed to such <hi>Disloyal</hi> and <hi>Republican Discourses,</hi> till their Ears were Violated by this <hi>Imposter,</hi> who could design nothing but mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief by it; for in a <hi>Monarchical Government,</hi> God's Vicegerency ought not to be delegated to any other Head but what is Anointed, nor unaccountably scat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered among the Multitude: For as Dividing a Power which is only safe by being <hi>Intire,</hi> derogates from the King's Supremacy; so it is destructive to the <hi>Peoples Liberty,</hi> as it Intoxicates them, and makes them stagger from one Form of Government to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94176:9"/> till their Divisions, as a Punishment for their Fickleness, sinks them at last under an <hi>Absolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Pretence of Exalting a <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pular Power,</hi> could have no other Aim in the <hi>Preacher,</hi> than to create Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousies between the King and his People: For as they cannot allay the false <hi>Fears</hi> they are decoyed into, without Undutiful Resentments: So the King cannot brook <hi>Competitors</hi> in Power and Prerogative; and therefore the <hi>Preacher</hi> in playing the <hi>Inferior</hi> Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers against the <hi>Head,</hi> could have no design but the Destruction of the whole Body: For this is an Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Maxime, <hi>That they who endeavour to submit Kings, rather than themselves, are laying the Foundation of Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Confusion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One Argument our Case-harden'd <hi>Predicant</hi> made use of, to prove the Power was in the People, was from <hi>Jethro</hi>'s Advising <hi>Moses</hi> to Ease himself; by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing Inferiour Magistrates to Hear and Determine lesser Differences among the People: Which is such a positive Contradiction to what he was advancing, that in the whole <hi>Book of God,</hi> he could not have found an Instance more directly <hi>Opposite</hi> to his Notion, than the <hi>Absolute Authority</hi> that <hi>Moses</hi> exercis'd over the Tribes of <hi>Israel:</hi> And at this no wise Man will won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for <hi>Scriptura</hi> is so much out of our <hi>Preachers</hi> way, as he never <hi>Blunders</hi> more, as when he thinks to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port his s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aking 'cause from those Sacred Oracles; so that unless he acquit himself better for time to come, than he either did at St. <hi>Mary le Bow, Jan.</hi> 30. 1693. or at St. <hi>Margaret</hi>'s <hi>Westminster, Jan.</hi> 30. 1699. he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:94176:9"/> will scarce be capable of any better Preferment, than Chaplain in Ordinary to the <hi>Calves Head Club,</hi> that Feast, and Rejoice, in Memory of the most Barbarous Murder that the Sun ever saw, or M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n or Devils were capable of committing.</p>
            <p>Sermons generally beget or lose their Esteem, by their being suted, or running Counter to the Occasion for which they were intended, and how our <hi>Preacher</hi> acquitted himself in this particular, is apparent. It was a Day of Humiliation for the <hi>Murder of a King by Rebellious Subjects,</hi> and instead of humbly perswading his Auditors to be Zealous in the Discharge of that Duty, he Preaches up the exploded <hi>Opinions</hi> that were the Occasions of that <hi>Bloody Tragedy,</hi> a Lawless Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and the pretended Power of the People began the War, Murdered the King, and brought the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under a Cruel and Barbarous Vassalage to the Meanest of their Fellow Subjects, and his knowing the same Causes will for ever produce the same Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, made these the main things he insisted upon on the Thirtieth of <hi>January,</hi> whereon nothing like a <hi>Christian,</hi> or indeed a Man, besides his wretched self, could have plaid the <hi>Buffoon</hi> and <hi>Incendiary</hi> at so mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a rate, upon so <hi>Solemn</hi> and <hi>Sad</hi> and Occasion, as brought together that August Assembly before whom he Preach'd; tho' as another Specimen of his Defence, he was pleased, for Reasons best known to himself, to omit praying for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and every Branch of the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> which I believe, was scarce omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon that Day by any Preacher in <hi>England</hi> besides himself.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:94176:10"/>
            <p>But it seems our Preacher's great Design, <hi>was, to Preach down the Observation of the Day;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore instead of Declaiming against those <hi>Black Counsels</hi> and <hi>Accursed Practices,</hi> which finish'd the last part of this <hi>Blessed Monarch's</hi> Tragedy, and humbly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swading his <hi>Illustrious Auditory,</hi> as the Representa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Nation, to be most Industriously Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that the same Chimerical Designs and <hi>Antomonar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chical Principles,</hi> which then Inspired so many Ill Men, Misled so many Good Men, and cost a Good King so Dear; might once more <hi>Rivive,</hi> and Insi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate themselves again, under the <hi>same,</hi> or <hi>Newer,</hi> and <hi>Craftier Disguises,</hi> and find an opportunity to attempt the like Mischiefs, he would have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded his <hi>Honourable Auditors,</hi> That the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of this Fast, which has always been Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiously observed by all <hi>Parliaments,</hi> should be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly Abolished, and Raced out of the <hi>English</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender.</p>
            <p>A Bold and Presumptious Undertaking, to Dictate to that <hi>Wise and Honourable Assembly;</hi> and whilst he was performing his part of the Office appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Day, to declaim against the Observation of it: Least Guilty Consciences should be disturb'd, by the Remembrance of this <hi>Eternal Reproach,</hi> which though an <hi>Indemplity</hi> has Pardoned, no Oblivion will ever be able to <hi>Deface,</hi> is so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable, that none but himself can assign a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son for.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94176:10"/>
            <p>What could Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> read in the Faces of these Wise and Loyal Senators, that could tempt him to such an Extravagant Conceit, that they would hearken to such an Infamous Proposal? What one thing have they ever done that might <hi>Countenance</hi> such a Presumption, that none but a Man of Mr. <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens</hi>'s Forehead durst have offer'd to a Parliament, without expecting to be made an Example to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity?</p>
            <p>Had our Presumptuous and saucy Holder-Forth but consulted with our English History, he might have found that a Parliament had the Memory of <hi>Charles</hi> the First in such a great Esteem, that they Voted Seventy Thousand Pound to build him a Monument, and to pay the Charge of Removing his Body from <hi>Windsor</hi> to <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Just. Defence, <hi>p. 200.</hi>
               </note> by which it appears, that the whole Kingdom thought nothing too much for expiating the Guilt, and Honouring the Memory of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince, which had been so Barbarously trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And tho' the Bill did not pass for the <hi>Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> yet the same Parliament had done another thing before, which in spight of all Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi>'s Arguments against it, may out-last all of that Kind in <hi>Westminster,</hi> or elsewhere in the whole Nation, <hi>viz. <hi>Enacted, That the Day of that horrid Patricide, be observed as a solemn Fast through the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for ever.</hi>
               </hi> And doubtless could they have fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seen, that any Person would have taken the Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to Asperse his Memory, or to have given Reasons for the <hi>Non Observance of this Fast,</hi> it would
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94176:11"/> have been Voted no less Treasonable than his Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But let us hear Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi>'s Reasons for its Abolition. And the first was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Because it creates Animosities among the</hi> People; which is a very weak Argument, since the very <hi>Abolition</hi> of the Fast would have furnish'd them with a Subject to keep up the Popular Animosities, greater than ever the Observation of the Day can pretend to. In which no question but Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> will have his Share, for endeavouring to obliterate the Remembrance and Detestation of a Crime, that the Wisdom of the Nation have <hi>Enacted to continue for ever,</hi> and peradventure he may live to be poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at in the Streets saying, <hi>That is the Man that At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to put down the Aniversary Fast for the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of</hi> Charles the First, and by this means like <hi>Er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stratus</hi> may be remembred till Time shall be no more; besides, could our Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cher have obtain'd his end, an almost Twenty Years <hi>Rebellion,</hi> with the Miseries, Calamities and Desolations that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied Us will for ever keep up Animosities, tho' there were no such Day in the Calender as the 30th of <hi>January:</hi> And therefore with Respect to Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi>'s Project, I think the best way to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguish the Memory of that Guilty Day, <hi>Is to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor and Utterly forsake the Principles, that prompted Ill Men to Commit so Inhumane and Barbarous a Crime;</hi> for as long as Men will be Arraigning Governments. Trampling upon the Power of Kings, and making all publick Distractions, concur in making way to their beloved <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Usurpation,</hi> others will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better grounds Reply, That God is making In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisition
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:94176:11"/> for Blood, and that the Murder of our late Sovereign is Required, and Visited upon this present Generation.</p>
            <p>Another Reason assigned by our Preacher for the <hi>Non-Observance of this Day of Humiliation,</hi> was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause all the Bloody Actors in that Fatal Stroke were <hi>Dead,</hi> and the Memory of their Crimes ought to be Buried with them: Which Argument is as Weak and Feeble as the Other, unless he could prove, That the Principles by which those Regicides Acted, were as surely Damn'd to all Eternity, as the Authors of them are Dead: For till then, the Fast ought to continue, like a Bush-stuck up by a Charitable Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veller in a Quick-Sand, to Warn Men of the Sin and Danger, which those Ill Men by espousing Ill Principles, were led into; for, as I have said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what has been done, may be done again, and the same Causes will for ever produce the same Effects.</p>
            <p>Now to shew that these Accursed Principles are at present more predominant than they were 1642; which I can ascribe to nothing but the Looseness and Irreligion of the Age, I would ask Mr. <hi>Stephens,</hi> Whether the <hi>Commonwealth Party</hi> are not now more Numerous, Insolent, and since they joyn'd with the <hi>Jacobites</hi> more <hi>formidable</hi> too, than in any King's Reign whatsoever? And also I would know, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they do not take the same Methods, to Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Present Government under <hi>William the Third,</hi> as their Predecessors did under his Royal Grandfather <hi>Charles the First?</hi> And I heartily Wish this Evil be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:94176:12"/> not so long neglected till it be grown past Redress, or Cure.</p>
            <p>Are not our Republican Scriblers the Common Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of all the Virulent Pamphlets against the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? Who by Reporting what is False and Perverting what is True, are forcing Unsteady Men upon the Rock, on which their Fathers were Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrackt.</p>
            <p>Has not a Bold <hi>Rennigado Irish Popish Priest</hi> Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Milton</hi>'s Life who Vindicated the Murder of the <hi>Lord's Anointed,</hi> and gives that Wretch many high Elogiums, that once occasion'd several Hours De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates in the <hi>House of Commons:</hi> Whether he should not be <hi>Hang'd</hi> for what he had Written, in Justifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of that Abominable Parricide, and had some of his <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Admired Books</hi> Burnt by the Hands of the <hi>Common Hangman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not all that Vile Man's Works now <hi>Reprint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> And for fear they should not do Mischief e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that way, Is not an Abridgment of the most <hi>Poysonous Passages,</hi> put all together in the Account of his Life?</p>
            <p>And which is no less observable than all the rest; Are not all these Collections made by a <hi>Priest in</hi> Romish <hi>Orders?</hi> And who, for ought we know, tho' h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts the Part of a <hi>Republican,</hi> may be a <hi>Romish</hi> Emmissary, sent hither on purpose to Embroyl our Affairs, and to Divide us among our Selves, that at last we may become a Prey to the Common Enemy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:94176:12"/> of our Nation and Religion; for this is but the Old Game Renewed, and 'twould be a Wonder, while some are Rending our Government to pieces, if the <hi>Papists</hi> should not have their Wolves in Sheeps Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among us, to hasten our Ruine.</p>
            <p>Further, are not <hi>Ludlow</hi>'s <hi>Letters,</hi> and <hi>Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s <hi>Commonwealth of</hi> Oceana, in every Hand? And is any thing so common as Calves-Head Clubs of Commonwealths Men, who Nightly Assemble to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote that Interest? Which, I think, if seriously considered, there is as much Reason now as ever, to Antidote this Infection, and not to Gratifie the Preacher in his Intolerable Impertinencies.</p>
            <p>But to turn the Tables upon Mr. <hi>Stephens,</hi> who suffer'd himself to be made a Property for the Service of a Faction; there can be no greater Argument, That the Republicans are very busie in setting up their <hi>Good Old Cause,</hi> than what relates to himself: For some of his Party, as soon as he had leave to Preach before the Honourable House of Commons, Industriously spreading a Report, What Wonders Master <hi>Stephens</hi> would perform, in Order to Quash the Observation of the <hi>Fast</hi> upon the Thirtieth of <hi>January.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He sold the Copy of his Sermon to a Bookseller, before it was Preached, as I am Credibly Informed, for Five and Twenty Pounds: Far fetch'd and Dear
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:94176:13"/> bought, are only fit for Ladies and Commonwealths Men, who never stick at the Price of any thing that may be serviceable to their Faction, which if the Bookseller is not well assured of, he has certainly catch'd a <hi>Tartar;</hi> for never Man heard of such an Extravagant Rate given for a Single Sermon, which can only make him amends by the Badness of it. But now as Matters are Circumstantiated, and the Preacher finds himself mistaken in the Strength of his Faction, it may so sink the Value of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that like the rest of their Republican Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, it must at last be Printed by a <hi>Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I as Briefly as I could, Animadverted upon this <hi>Two-handed Sermon,</hi> in which I had been more particular, but for two Reasons.</p>
            <p>First, Because that Reverend, Pious, and Learned Prelate, His Grace the Lord Arcbishop of <hi>York,</hi> Preached the same Day, and upon the same Text, before the Righr Honourable the House of Lords, in <hi>Westminster-Abby;</hi> and the Lords having desired His Grace to Print His Sermon, you will find in that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scourse the Duty enjoyn'd in the Text, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Observation of the Day, Rescued from the Impertinent, Clandestine, and Dangerous Surmises of Mr. <hi>Stephens.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:94176:13"/>
            <p>Secondly, Because the Honourable the <hi>House of Commons,</hi> before whom his Sermon was Preached, have shewed their Resentments of it, in a Vote and Resolve worthy of Themselves, and Eternal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. To which I refer you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>